<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-21T16:04:16-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mumlennial</title><subtitle>Millenial mumming and money.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Investing in the S&amp;amp;P/ASX 20</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/20/investing-in-the-s&p-asx-20/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Investing in the S&amp;P/ASX 20" /><published>2019-01-20T14:23:27-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-20T14:23:27-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/20/investing-in-the-s&amp;p-asx-20</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/20/investing-in-the-s&amp;p-asx-20/">&lt;p&gt;Being an expat means juggling finances across two countries, until now I haven’t really being paying attention to my money in Australia but since I’ve recently been educating myself on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FIRE_movement&quot;&gt;FIRE&lt;/a&gt; movement, I wanted to make sure I was putting my Australian dollars to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, being somewhat of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bogleheads.org/&quot;&gt;Boglehead&lt;/a&gt; my first inclination was to invest everything in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vanguardinvestments.com.au/retail/ret/investments/product.html#/fundDetail/etf/portId=8205/?overview&quot;&gt;VAS&lt;/a&gt; the Vanguard ETF which tracks the S&amp;amp;P/ASX 300 Index. I talked to my tax accountant who is an Aussie herself but has been living and working in LA and specialises in Aussie expats living over here in the US to see if there would be any tax implications with this approach. She advised me that since the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Financial_crisis_of_2007%E2%80%932008&quot;&gt;Global Financial Crisis&lt;/a&gt; the US has imposed some a number of reporting requirements for US residents who have foreign bank accounts and investments and that index funds are classified as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://thunfinancial.com/home/american-expat-financial-advice-research-articles/why-americans-should-never-ever-own-shares-in-a-non-us-incorporated-mutual-fund/&quot;&gt;PFIC&lt;/a&gt; (Passive Foreign Investment Company). This type of investment not only meant high taxation rates but remaining in compliance was a very onerous task (IRS estimates it will take a person 40 hours or more to fill out one PFIC form) which would cost me more in accountant fees than I would receive in profit! Good to know!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I quickly scratched that idea and looked for an alternative way to get a slice of the S&amp;amp;P/ASX 300 Index. Being a longtime &lt;a href=&quot;https://barefootinvestor.com/&quot;&gt;Barefoot Investor&lt;/a&gt; fan, I had already heard about a company called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.afi.com.au/Investment-performance.aspx&quot;&gt;Australian Foundation Investment Company&lt;/a&gt;. Scott Pape &lt;a href=&quot;https://barefootinvestor.com/how-to-invest-guide/listed-investment-companies/&quot;&gt;has recommended them&lt;/a&gt; for a long time to folks who are new to investing and want to get started. From their website AFIC:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a diversified portfolio numbering around 100 of Australia’s major companies (gets me the diversification aspect I’m after)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;management fees - 0.14% for the financial year to 30 June 2018 (low fees, in fact its the same as VAS)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a dividend reinvestment plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew that AFIC was a Listed Investment Company so I wanted to double check it wasn’t also considered a PFIC and turns out it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atlaswealth.com.au/big-tax-bills-surfacing-for-expat-clients/&quot;&gt;is&lt;/a&gt; :( Back to the drawing board!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point it seems I’m going to just have to build up a diversified portfolio of individual stocks in order to remain in compliance. A portfolio of a slice of the top 20 companies of the ASX (all bluechip companies with a solid track record) seems like a good plan so my first stop was to see how the S&amp;amp;P/ASX 20 tracked against the S&amp;amp;P/ASX 300 Index (my original desired portfolio). Jumping over to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?rlz=1C5CHFA_enUS781US781&amp;amp;tbm=fin&amp;amp;q=INDEXASX:+XTL&amp;amp;stick=H4sIAAAAAAAAAONgecRoyi3w8sc9YSmdSWtOXmNU4-IKzsgvd80rySypFJLgYoOy-KR4uLj0c_UNjJNNqyoLeAA_9trYOgAAAA&amp;amp;biw=1527&amp;amp;bih=762#scso=_e9BFXJPaL8K0_AaC6pDoBg2:0&amp;amp;smids=/m/03gv32v&amp;amp;wptab=COMPARE&quot;&gt;Google Finance&lt;/a&gt; I made this comparison chart:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ASX20vASX300.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?rlz=1C5CHFA_enUS781US781&amp;amp;tbm=fin&amp;amp;q=INDEXASX:+XTL&amp;amp;stick=H4sIAAAAAAAAAONgecRoyi3w8sc9YSmdSWtOXmNU4-IKzsgvd80rySypFJLgYoOy-KR4uLj0c_UNjJNNqyoLeAA_9trYOgAAAA&amp;amp;biw=1527&amp;amp;bih=762#scso=_e9BFXJPaL8K0_AaC6pDoBg2:0&amp;amp;smids=/m/03gv32v&amp;amp;wptab=COMPARE&quot;&gt;Google Finance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As predicted it tracks the S&amp;amp;P/ASX 300 quite closely and event looks like it trends a little higher (I kinda expected it to have higher highs and lower lows but it doesn’t).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found out that there was an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blackrock.com/au/individual/products/251921/ishares-ishares-s-and-p-asx-20-etf?locale=en_AU&amp;amp;switchLocale=y&amp;amp;siteEntryPassthrough=true&quot;&gt;iShares ETF&lt;/a&gt; that tracked this index, so I figured I would just use their weightings in my own portfolio. The holdings look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe frameborder=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/e/2PACX-1vS5uog_dKUbkWn-7iwq-ZxvtWUs69uu5ePT-dbHsSf6vh0f3Yfboello9JyB2wlRch2E8_WdaK7EsOV/pubhtml?gid=2077100303&amp;amp;single=true&amp;amp;widget=true&amp;amp;headers=false&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this plan of course wouldn’t be a great idea if you only had a few thousand to invest as its going to incur higher brokerage fees than just trading on a single index ETF. I trade with CMC so my brokerage will be 11 x 20 = $220AUD. The downside of maintaining my own portfolio is that it will be much harder to keep in balance of these ratios when I want to buy/sell but as owning individual stocks is my only option, I’m ok with this compromise. I’ll plan on signing up for DRP on each of the stocks that offer them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is my current investment plan for the money I have in Australia but I do like to quantify decisions with numbers so lets take a look at my two options, option A leave the money in a high interest savings account and option B investment in the S&amp;amp;P/ASX 20. We can assume it will be a longterm investment 5 years and for examples sake we’ll use $100 000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option A: high interest savings account&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
amount: $100 000&lt;br /&gt;
interest rate: 2.87% p.a&lt;br /&gt;
amount after 5 years: $115,411&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option B: investment in the S&amp;amp;P/ASX 20&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Past performance is no indicator of future performance however we do know that given enough time the stock market always goes up. I found the below 5 year annualized rate of return on &lt;a href=&quot;https://us.spindices.com/indices/equity/sp-asx-20&quot;&gt;Morningstar&lt;/a&gt; (I believe this rate includes dividends as well as capital growth).&lt;br /&gt;
amount: $100 000&lt;br /&gt;
past 5 year annualized return: 4.76%&lt;br /&gt;
estimated amount after 5 years: $126,176.20&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it would be interesting too, to compare performance against the S&amp;amp;P 500:
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ASX20vS&amp;amp;P500.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://us.spindices.com/indices/equity/sp-asx-20&quot;&gt;Morningstar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a long term investor in the stock market and am happy to ride out any troughs so it makes sense to me to have my money work for me in the stock market instead of leaving it in a high interest savings account. Also it’s worth pointing out that inflation in Australia is currently &lt;a href=&quot;https://tradingeconomics.com/australia/inflation-cpi&quot;&gt;around 2%&lt;/a&gt; so leaving the money in UBank doesn’t grow it by very much at all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="PFIC" /><category term="tax" /><category term="investment" /><summary type="html">Being an expat means juggling finances across two countries, until now I haven’t really being paying attention to my money in Australia but since I’ve recently been educating myself on the FIRE movement, I wanted to make sure I was putting my Australian dollars to work.</summary></entry></feed>